A Guide to the Civil War letters to William S. Dennett
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Civil War letters to William S. Dennett 1861-1865
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
1255
This collection consists of 41 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Aquisition Information
This collection was purchased from Fred Rouleau, Kennebunk, Maine, by the University of Virginia Library on October 28, 1941.
Scope and Content Information
Correspondents discuss camp life; winter quarters; marches; deserters with forged papers and the shooting of deserters; illnesses and deaths in battles; prisoners of war, particularly the care and transportation of wounded and ill Confederates; picket duty and friendly exchanges across the lines; hostile behavior against African American troops; England's attitude; a comparison of McClellan vs Hooker; and opinion of Halleck.
Engagements mentioned include Harper's Ferry, Antietam, Fredericksburg and Union attempts to bridge the Rappahannock, Chancellorsville and retreat, destruction of Yorktown, and events in Grant's march around Richmond.
Correspondents include Union soldiers George B. Elmore, 61st Regiment New York [Engineers?]; Joel W. Gaylord; A. H. Mayo, engineer; Thaddeus [K.?] Pendleton, Engineers Headquarters, Falmouth; and Samuel W. Richards, Sanitary Commission.
There is also a single letter from T.S.L. to his brother and sister, Baltimore, October 12, 1861, discussing the fortifications about Baltimore, where they will be ready to mount the cannon in two or three weeks, and his work repairing army wagons. He has also heard that an expedition of 50,000 men, including the Eighth and Ninth Maine Regiments, has left from Annapolis for an unknown destination.
Contents List
- From George B. Elmore, 2nd Lt., Co. K, 61st Regiment, New York Volunteers 1862 Oct 12
  Caldwell's Brigade, Hancock's Division, at camp near Harper's Ferry -- describes hideous fight at Harper's Ferry, where his regiment lost half its number but was first to occupy the place after its inglorious surrender. Talks about the battle at Antietam, where some of the Rebels asked us to pray for them and we did in a manner they did not like, mentions he has received no pay for seven months.
- From George B. Elmore, in camp near Falmouth, Va. 1862 Dec 18
  Congratulates Denton on his promotion to surgeon's orderly and describes intense fighting at Fredericksburg, where the 15th New York Engineers got badly cut up while attempting to throw a bridge across the Rappahannock under heavy Rebel fire.
- From Thaddeus K. Pendleton, Headquarters U.S. Engineers, Falmouth, Va. 1862 Dec 22
  lists names of those in the company who have died, been taken prisoner or run away; tells of leaving Antietam for Harper's Ferry and describes in detail difficulties of throwing bridges across the Rappahannock and then taking them up again under fire as the enemy advanced; asks What advantage was gained by our troops going over there? None-only we made a fool of ourselves and left a chance for the Rebels to laugh at us.
- From George B. Elmore in camp near Falmouth, Va. 1862 Dec ?
  Mentions he is still waiting for pay after nine months; says Well, here we are on the banks of the Rappahannock looking down in contempt upon the miserable city. Old Burntsides (sic) says to the Rebbs-now you fire a gun at me and down goes your town. Rebb Gen. Lee says now you come any further and down goes your house and so on, but we don't see any house go down.
- From Thaddeus K. Pendleton, Headquarters Engineers, Falmouth, Va. 1863 Jan 5
  Is happy to report that back pay ( 6 months) was distributed day before New Year's; I find it very inconvenient to be without pay for so long I could get along well enough if I could only get tobacco, for you know when you was with us that if a soldier gets out of that article, time hangs more heavily on his hands; describes tents being erected on both sides of the river by the Feds and the Rebs and is puzzled as to why the Rebel tents seem superior; huts also being put up and spirits of troops excellent.
- From S. W. Richards, Sanitary Commission, Washington, D.C. 1863 Feb 15
  Describes the activities of two former comrades-Harry [J] Eager of Co. A and [ ? ] Lane of Co. C., who forged discharge papers and put on citizen's clothes. Both were found out, arrested, and Lane attempted escape by jumping out a third story window and breaking both his legs. Also tells of visits to Bacon's Shotacaryprop.
- From George B. Elmore, camp near Falmouth, Va. 1863 Mar 8
- From George B. Elmore, camp near Falmouth, Va. 1863 Apr 21
- From Samuel W. Richards, Sanitary Commission, Washington D.C. 1863 May 7
  Tells of transfers of friends; reports that Maj. [ ] Gerber was court-martialed at West Point for rascally thieving; contrasts Generals McClellan and Hooker.
- From George B. Elmore, at camp near Falmouth 1863 May 10
  Vividly describes the fight at Chancellorsville and the retreat of his unit twenty-one miles in seven hours with heavy knapsacks, 8 days rations and the mud 18 inches deep-the Rebs shelling at every step.
- From S. W. Richards, Sanitary Commission, Washington, D.C. 1863 May 17
  Response to Dennett's queries about jobs; mentions that Hooker and Halleck have been to see the President and he expects Hooker to be in action before the week is out.
- From George B. Elmore at camp near Falmouth, Va. 1863 June 3
  Describes being very ill with a bilious fever and hears Rebels are showing signs of attack.
- From Thaddeus K. Pendleton, Headquarters, U.S. Engineers, Falmouth, Va. 1863 June 6
  Tells in some detail attempts of Federal troops to throw bridges across the Rappahannock under heavy Rebel gunfire; Capt. C.C. Cross of his battalion is killed during this action which he describes as a great loss.
- From George B. Elmore at camp near Falmouth, Va. 1863 June 12
  Writes about a Union soldier taken prisoner at Chancellorsville who was marched to Richmond and later exchanged; says prisoner told of horrors of the march and reports that Richmond has many more union sympathizers than some cities in the north.
- From Thaddeus K. Pendleton, Headquarters, U.S. Engineers, Beverly Ford, Va. 1863 July 30
  Thinks it a pity Lee was ever permitted to re-cross the Potomac; talks of pickets of the enemy camp being within 200 yards and how men on both sides exchange papers and news one day and fire upon each other the next; discusses the drafting of more men.
- From George B. Elmore, Washington, D.C. 1863 Aug 13
  Mentions suffering sunstroke while marching 20 or 30 miles in heat as rear guard to army of the Potomac.
- From Thaddeus K. Pendleton, Headquarters, U.S. Engineers, Rappahannock Station 1863 Aug 16
  Relatively quiet along the Potomac; his battalion has thrown four pontoon bridges across the river; reports being fired upon by the Rebels, but hastily, with no time taken for reloading as at Fredericksburg; refers to Copperheads as snakes.
- From A.H. Mayo, camp of engineers near Beverly Ford 1863 Aug 16
- From Thaddeus K. Pendleton, Headquarters of U.S. Engineers, Rappahannock Station 1863 Aug 26
  Describes deserters being rounded up and shot, mainly from the 2nd brigade, 1st division, 5th corps; intends to go watch as he feels something must be done to stop deserters; reflects upon his feelings as a native of Britain and a Union soldier and comments upon England's attitude toward the war; discusses mutual antagonism of England and U.S. toward Copperheads.
- From A. H. Mayo, camp of Engineers near Rappahannock Station 1863 Aug 31
  praises the work of B. Company; did not attend the shooting of deserters but those who did described it as a solemn occasion with 35 bullets passing through them and killing them instantly.
- From Samuel W. Richards, Sanitary Commission, Washington, D.C. 1863 Sep 3
  Mentions load of kindlings and torpedoes under the railroad bridge at Rappahannock station ready to touch off at any moment.
- From A. H. Mayo, camp near Culpeper, Va. 1863 Sep 3
  Tells of marches back and forth to Culpeper from Rappahannock Station. I suppose we have to do it to while away the time.-thinks Culpeper is about the meanest place that I have been in Virginia.
- From Thaddeus K. Pendleton, Headquarters, U.S. Engineers, Culpeper 1863 Oct 1
  Thinks a long march of his company is about to take place, possibly toward Richmond.
- From A.H. Mayo, camp near Centreville 1963 Oct 17
  Thinks troops generally happy after a long march and tells of individual activities in camp.
- From Joel W. Gaylord 1863 Dec 20
  old blown up, torn up Yorktown, describes vividly destruction in Yorktown from fires and explosion.
- From Joel W. Gaylord, Gloucester Point, Va. 1864 Jan 14
  References to his camp where a Negro regiment has been assigned and stories about the difficulties of moving his regiment to the outside of the fort, where the Negroes were ordered inside. Says the white man is not as good as the Negro anymore; describes quarreling between the two regiments and the burning by the white soldiers of some of the tents and buildings inside the fort before turning it over to the Negroes.
- From Joel W. Gaylord, Gloucester Point, Va. 1864 Mar 1
  Gives an account of raids up and down the Peninsula and the destruction of the Gloucester Court House.
- From Joel W. Gaylord, Fort Keys, near Gloucester Point, Va. 1864 Mar 20
  Writes that he has been on many peninsula marches but none before where he has been exposed to so much hardship; has been on picket duty ten days at a time; reports men have been dying very fast-139 thus far- with one of them being a soldier shot at Yorktown for letting a prisoner escape.
- From Joel W. Gaylord, Fort Yorktown, Va. 1864 May 4
  Reports the arrival of 75 thousand troops in the last 15 days, with many leaving on transports; says things are being conducted very quietly but rumors are that they are determined to have a ball in Richmond.
- From Lewellyn Libbey to Aunt Mary 1864 July 8
  Hampton Hospital, Va., tells Aunt Mary he has been ill but is better; writes-- Mary, I have made up my mind to take as good care of my life as I can now. For you know that life is sweet to me about this time. I have been in a number of bad places since I have been out here this time and come out all right and now if I can get out of a hard chance, I shall do it, for, as [E.B. Prime] says I had rather be a coward than a dead hero.
- From Joel W. Gaylord, Point Lookout, Hammond Hospital 1864 July 14
  Has been near death from severe illness, which he describes; tells of transfers to various hospitals when his camp was evacuated; is reduced to 94 1/2 pounds; 18,000 sick Rebels have been moved from the hospital to Elmira, N.Y.
- From Joel W. Gaylord, Point Lookout, Va., Hammond Hospital, Va. 1864 July [?]
  Still ill; congratulates Dennett on his marriage July 23; describes vividly a tornado that morning which struck the dead house first, smashed other buildings and struck part of the hospital; complains he has received no pay since January 1.
- From Pvt. George B. Elmore, Oxford Crossroads near Great Falls, Md. 1864 Aug 17
  Outside of Washington, D.C., writes that he has reenlisted for 100 days.
- From Joel W. Gaylord, Point Lookout, Va., Hammond Hospital 1864 Aug 24
  Says news from our army has been cheering from every source; asks Dennett to loan him $3 as he has not been paid in 8 months.
- From George B. Elmore, Great Falls, Md. 1864 Aug 27
  Describes his duties of picketing and scouting and marvels that the enemy appears as vigorous as ever; comments on the long, unanticipated duration of the struggle, and remarks that the double purpose of the war now is to revenge the deaths of brothers who have fallen and to tear from the grasp of treason the land which must be free.
- From Joel W. Gaylord, Point Lookout, Va., Hammond Hospital 1864 Aug 31
  thanks Denton and his wife and her mother for the money they have sent and describes walking one-half mile to a sort of hotel, where he purchased ham and eggs, coffee with milk in it, homemade bread, more coffee, beefsteak, more coffee and a piece of pie.
- (Continued in previous letter) received two months pay yesterday. 1864 Sep 1
- From George B. Elmore, near Muddy Branch, Md. 1864 Sep 6
  We are now on the outpost--the whole army of Washington is under our care--a fearful responsibility. Surely history cannot fail to mention Company G hereafter. The very trees seem to tremble at our approach. General Early the Rebel has fallen back before us as expected and all is quiet along the Potomac.
- From Lewellyn Libbey to Aunt Mary 1864 Sep 12
  Hampton Hospital, expects the hardest battle of the war to start soon.
- From Joel W. Gaylord, battlefield before Richmond 1864 Oct 21
  Describes leaving the hospital September 29 with 300 sick Rebel soldiers on board who were paroled for sixty days with the expectation of being exchanged -- dead men nearly, for they had been at that point 18 mos. Prisoners and sick all the time; describes reaching his regiment a dirty set of men 3 or 4 weeks without a change of clothes or tents; tells of an attack by Rebels and describes other vigorous fighting near Richmond; says most of the soldiers have voted but the vote will disappoint the north because McClellan's (Gen. George B.) stock has fallen since the Chicago convention.
- From Lewellyn Libbey to Aunt Mary 1865 Mar 9
  Chesapeake General Hospital, Fort Monroe, predicts war will be over in 6 months.